A Finding Aid to the Sylvia Snowden Papers, 1962-2017, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Sylvia Snowden papers
1962-2017
Archives of American Art
Snowden, Sylvia
AAA.snowsylv
Archival Resource Key
1.7 Linear feet
The papers of African American abstract painter Sylvia Snowden measure 1.7 linear feet and date from 1962 to 2017. The collection contains biographical material, including recorded interviews with Snowden; correspondence; material related to professional activities, including exhibitions and symposia; printed material; and photographic material, as well as one sketch.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Researchers interested in accessing born-digital records or audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Scope and Contents
The papers of African American abstract painter Sylvia Snowden measure 1.7 linear feet and date from 1962 to 2017. The collection contains biographical material, including recorded interviews with Snowden, resumes and chronologies, and certificates; correspondence with galleries and museums including M. Hanks Gallery and the Corcoran Gallery of Art; material related to professional activities, including exhibitions and symposia, and related audiovisual and born-digital materials; printed material, including exhibition invitations, exhibition catalogs, calendars, clippings, and magazines; and a small amount of photographic material, as well as one sketch.
Biographical / Historical
Sylvia Snowden (1942- ) is an African American abstract painter in Washington, D.C. known for her large mixed-media works that convey a sense of texture or the "feel of paint."
Snowden earned both a Bachelor and a Master of Fine Arts degree from Howard University. She also attended Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture in Maine and earned a certificate from le Grande Chaumière in Paris, France. She has served as an instructor, visiting lecturer, panelist, and artist-in-residence at universities, galleries, and art schools across the country and internationally. Her work has been included in exhibitions at the National Gallery of Art, the Corcoran Gallery of Art, the National Museum of Women in the Arts, Parish Gallery, and the California African American Museum; as well as in exhibitions in Chile, the Netherlands, Ethiopia, Australia, the Bahamas, France, Mexico, Italy, and Japan.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Sylvia Snowden papers were donated in 2019 by Sylvia Snowden, as part of the Archives' African American Collecting Initiative funded by the Henry Luce Foundation.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged as five series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1962, 1985-2004 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1975-2005 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 3: Professional Activities, 1985-2017 (Box1; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1964-2017 (Boes 1-3, OV 4; 0.9 linear feet)
Series 5: Photographic Material and Artwork, 1989-2005 (Box 3; 0.1 linear feet)
Women artists; African American artists; Video recordings; Painters -- Washington (D.C.); Women painters; African American painters; Corcoran Gallery of Art; Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture; M. Hanks Gallery (Santa, Monica, Calif.)
- Biographical Material, 1962; 1985-2004; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains an address list; certificates; recorded interviews on VHS and a transcript of an interview with Sylvia Snowden that originally aired on NPR's All Things Considered; and copies of Snowden's resume and chronologies of her exhibitions.
  - Address List, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Certificates, 1962; 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes certificate from Académie de la Grande Chaumière and certificate of appreciation from the Anacostia Museum.
  - Interview Recording, "Sylvia Snowden Interview — Raw Footage Lancaster", undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Interview Recording, What Follows... Interview with Chuck Forsman at University of Colorado, Boulder, circa 1990; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Interview Transcript, Sylvia Snowden on Weekend All Things Considered, 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Resumes and Chronologies, 1985-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1975-2005; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  This series contains Snowden's correspondence with galleries and museums, including M. Hanks Gallery and the Corcoran Gallery of Art.
  - Corcoran Gallery of Art, 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes correspondence related to Snowden's exhibition, Malik Farewell, Till We Meet Again. Also includes a lsit of artwork loaned to the Corcoran.
  - M. Hanks Gallery (Erick Hanks), 1988-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Also includes printed material.
  - Judith Wilson, 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Includes photocopies of works written by Wilson.
  - General Correspondence, A-I, 1975-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Also includes photocopy of guest book for Abstract in Black exhibition at School 33 Art Center.
  - General Correspondence, L-P, 1985-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - General Correspondence, R-Y, 1986-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Professional Activities, 1985-2017; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1
  Included in this series are materials related to Sylvia Snowden's exhibitions, speaking engagements, and fellowships. Also included are materials related to sale of her work and teaching at the University of the District of Columbia. Files may contain correspondence, contracts, invoices, printed material, and photographs. This series also includes audiovisual and born-digital material.
  - The African American Art World in Twentieth-Century Washington, DC Symposium, National Gallery of Art, 2017; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Artist Statements, circa 2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Black Women Artists/1987 (1987), Museum of the National Center of Afro-American Artists, Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - DC Commission on the Arts and Humanities Grants-in-Aid Fellowship, 1988-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Includes application materials, as well as financial documentation for grant period.
  - Gathered Visions: Selected Works by African American Women Artists (1990-1991), Anacostia Museum, Smithsonian Institution, 1990-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Introspection: Contemporary Art by Americans and Brazilians of African Descent (1989), California Afro-American Museum, 1988-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Also includes correspondence and poster related to the California Institute Intercultural Arts Project visiting artist residency.
  - Invoices and Insurance Certificate, 1989-2016; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Includes material related to the creation of Sylvia Snowden's website.
  - Loan Forms, 1985-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Malik Farewell, Till We Meet Again Recordings, 2000; Archival Resource Key; 3 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 21)
    One tape labeled "Malik Farewell Sylvia Snowden Corcoran Gallery." Unlabeled cassettes include one television segment about the exhibition and one other recording that appears to be at the gallery.
  - Painting in Your Voice: A Black Woman's Guide to Developing an Artistic Career Book Project, circa 2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Sales Records, 1987-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Slide Lists, 1990; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Also includes label from National Museum of Women in the Arts.
  - Sylvia Snowden Portfolio, 1992-circa 2010; Archival Resource Key; 3 Electronic discs (CD) (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Includes price lists, list of selected exhibitions, and printed material. Portfolio discs contain artist statement, curriculam vitae, images, and a slideshow.
  - University of Colorado at Boulder Visiting Artist Program, 1989-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - University of the District of Columbia, 1987-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Includes personnel and payment forms; memos and correspondence; and academic calendar.
- Printed Material, 1964-2017; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.9 Linear feet Boxes 1-3, OV 4
  This series includes calendars, clippings, announcements and invitations to Sylvia Snowden exhibitions, exhibition catalogs, magazines, newsletters, and press releases.
  - Calendar, Baltimore Black Arts Calendar, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Calendar, Visions of 1993: A Calendar of Frameable Art by African American Women, Archival Resource Key (Oversize 4)
  - Clippings, 1975-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Clippings, 1979-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Oversize Clippings, 1985-1994; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 4)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Invitations, 1970-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Invitations, 2000-2016; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1964-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1987-1995; 2016; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
  - Magazines, ARTnews, 2005-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Magazines, Art in America, 2005-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Magazines, New Art Examiner, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Magazines and Journals, 1989-1992; 2002-2017; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Newsletters and Bulletins, 1964; 1984-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Includes Skowhegan School of Painting & Sculpture bulletin, brochure, and alumni newsletter.
  - Press Release and Flyers, Second Annual Arts Exhibition, The Association of Black Arts/East and Thirdworld Museum IIIrd, circa 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Press Releases, 1987-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Photographic Material and Artwork, 1989-2005; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 3
  This small series includes photographs, negatives, and slides of Snowden's artwork and of an exhibition, likely Malik Farewell, Till We Meet Again. Also included is one unidentified sketch.
  - Photographs, Exhibition, 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Photographs of guests viewing exhibition, likely Malik Farewell, Till We Meet Again.
  - Photographs, Works of Art, 1989-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Includes photographs, slides, and negatives.
  - Sketch, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)